Guide to the Henry O'Reilly Papers 1819-1880 (Bulk 1844-1860) MS 464
New-York Historical Society
- Series VI: New York State Agricultural Society, 1841-1856, Series VI is comprised of documents pertaining to various activities of the New York State Agricultural Society, of which O'Reilly was recording secretary. It includes material on the New York State Agricultural Fair of 1844.
  - Subseries VI.A: Correspondence, 1841-1847
    - Letters Sent, 1844-1847 (Box 40, Folder 4)
  - Subseries VI.B: Financial Documents, 1844
    - Financial Documents, 1844 (Box 40, Folder 5)
  - Subseries VI.C: Reports, 1843-1857
    - Reports, 1843-1857 (Box 40, Folder 6)
  - Subseries VI.D: Printed Material, 1843-1856
    - Printed Material, Undated (Box 40, Folder 7)
    - Printed Material, Undated (Box 40, Folder 8)
    - Printed Material, 1843 (Box 40, Folder 9)
    - Printed Material, 1844 (Box 40, Folder 10)
    - Printed Material, 1844 (Box 40, Folder 11)
    - Printed Material, 1845 (Box 40, Folder 12)
    - Printed Material, 1846 (Box 40, Folder 13)
    - Printed Material, 1856 (Box 40, Folder 14)
- Series VII: Politics, 1836-1857, Series VII documents O'Reilly's activities in New York State politics and his interest in promoting reform in the state and federal governments.
  - Subseries VII.A: Correspondence, 1838-1857 (Bulk 1838-1843)
    - Letters Received: Unidentified (Box 41, Folder 1)
    - Letters Received: A (Box 41, Folder 2)
    - Letters Received: B (Box 41, Folder 3)
    - Letters Received: C (Box 41, Folder 4)
    - Letters Received: D (Box 41, Folder 5)
    - Letters Received: E (Box 41, Folder 6)
    - Letters Received: G (Box 41, Folder 7)
    - Letters Received: H (Box 41, Folder 8)
    - Letters Received: J (Box 41, Folder 9)
    - Letters Received: K (Box 41, Folder 10)
    - Letters Received: L (Box 41, Folder 11)
    - Letters Received: M (Box 41, Folder 12)
    - Letters Received: P (Box 41, Folder 13)
    - Letters Received: R (Box 41, Folder 14)
    - Letters Received: S (Box 41, Folder 15)
    - Letters Received: T (Box 41, Folder 16)
    - Letters Received: U (Box 41, Folder 17)
    - Letters Received: W (Box 41, Folder 18)
    - Letters Sent, Undated (Box 41, Folder 19)
    - Letters Sent, 1839 (Box 41, Folder 20)
    - Letters Sent, 1840 (Box 41, Folder 21)
    - Letters Sent, 1842 (Box 41, Folder 22)
    - Letters Sent, 1857 (Box 41, Folder 23)
  - Subseries VII.B: Proceedings, Notes, Miscellaneous, 1840-1851 (Bulk 1849-1851)
    - Proceedings, Notes, Miscellaneous. (Box 41, Folder 24)
  - Subseries VII.C: Printed Material, 1836-1857
    - Printed Material, Undated (Box 41, Folder 25)
    - Printed Material, 1838 (Box 41, Folder 26)
    - Printed Material, 1843 (Box 41, Folder 27)
    - Printed Material, 1848 (Box 41, Folder 28)
- Series VIII: Post Office, Rochester, 1838-1844, This series contains documents pertaining to O'Reilly's daily activities and duties as Post Master of Rochester. It includes material concerning mail fraud, robberies and abuses in the post office.
  - Subseries VIII.A: Correspondence, 1838-1844
    - Letters Received, Undated (Box 42, Folder 1)
    - Letters Received, 1838 (Box 42, Folder 2)
    - Letters Received, 1839 (Box 42, Folder 3)
    - Letters Received, 1840 (Box 42, Folder 4)
    - Letters Received, 1840 (Box 42, Folder 5)
    - Letters Received, 1841 (Box 42, Folder 6)
    - Letters Received, 1842-1844 (Box 42, Folder 7)
    - Letters Sent, 1839-1842 (Box 42, Folder 8)
  - Subseries VIII.B: Legal Documents, 1839-1841
    - Legal Documents, 1839-1841 (Box 42, Folder 9)
  - Subseries VIII.C: Financial Documents, 1840-1841
    - Financial Documents, 1840-1841 (Box 42, Folder 10)
  - Subseries VIII.D: Printed Material, 1838-1855 (Bulk 1838-1841)
    - Printed Material, 1838-1855 (Box 42, Folder 11)
- Series IX: Common Schools, Rochester, 1838-1840, Series IX contains material pertaining to O'Reilly's interest in the Rochester public school system and his activities as trustee of School District No. 16 of Rochester.
  - Subseries IX.A: Correspondence, 1838-1840
    - Letters Received, Undated (Box 42, Folder 12)
    - Letters Received, 1838 (Box 42, Folder 13)
    - Letters Received, 1840 (Box 42, Folder 14)
    - Letters Sent, 1840 (Box 42, Folder 15)
  - Subseries IX.B: Reports and Notes, 1840, 1845
    - Reports and Notes, 1840, 1845 (Box 42, Folder 16)
  - Subseries IX.C: Financial Documents, 1839-1840
    - Financial Documents, 1839-1840 (Box 42, Folder 17)
  - Subseries IX.D: Printed Material, 1838-1840
    - Printed Material, 1838-1840 (Box 42, Folder 18)
- Series X: Rochester Athenaeum and Young Men's Association, 1838-1840, This series documents activities of the Rochester Athenaeum and Young Men's Association during O'Reilly's tenure as its president.
  - Subseries X.A: Correspondence, 1838-1840
    - Letters Received: Unidentified (Box 43, Folder 1)
    - Letters Received: B (Box 43, Folder 2)
    - Letters Received: C (Box 43, Folder 3)
    - Letters Received: Clark, George R. (Box 43, Folder 4)
    - Letters Received: Edwards, T.E. (Box 43, Folder 5)
    - Letters Received: F-M (Box 43, Folder 6)
    - Letters Received: P (Box 43, Folder 7)
    - Letters Received: R (Box 43, Folder 8)
    - Letters Received: S (Box 43, Folder 9)
    - Letters Received: Thayer, Wm. S. (Box 43, Folder 10)
    - Letters Received: V (Box 43, Folder 11)
    - Letters Received: W (Box 43, Folder 12)
    - Letters Sent, 1838-1840 (Box 43, Folder 13)
  - Subseries X.B: Minutes, 1839
    - Minutes, 1839 (Box 43, Folder 14)
  - Subseries X.C: Financial Documents, 1838-1840
    - Financial Documents, 1838-1840 (Box 43, Folder 15)
  - Subseries X.D: Notes, 1839-1840
    - Notes, 1839-1840 (Box 43, Folder 16)
  - Subseries X.E: Printed Material, 1839-1840
    - Printed Material, 1839-1840 (Box 43, Folder 17)
- Series XI: Western Virginia Lands, 1838-1856
  This series is comprised of documents pertaining to O'Reilly's interest in purchasing land in Western Virginia.
  - Subseries XI.A: General Correspondence, 1844-1851
    - General Correspondence, 1844-1851 (Box 43, Folder 18)
  - Subseries XI.B: Legal documents and notes, 1838-1847
    - Legal Documents and Notes, 1838-1847 (Box 43, Folder 19)
  - Subseries XI.C: Printed Material, 1844-1856
    - Printed Material, 1844-1856 (Box 43, Folder 20)
- Series XII: Albany Irish Repeal Association, 1843
  - Albany Irish Repeal Association, 1843 (Box 43, Folder 21)
- Series XIII: American Indians, 1838-1860
  - American Indians, 1838-1860 (Box 43, Folder 22)
- Series XIV: Deputy Collector and Inspector of District of Genesee, 1832-1842
  - Deputy Collector and Inspector of District of Genesee, 1832-1842 (Box 43, Folder 23)
- Series XV: Irish & American Steamship Company, 1851
  - Irish & American Steamship Company, 1851 (Box 43, Folder 24)
- Series XVI: New York Typographical Society, 1849
  - New York Typographical Society, 1849 (Box 43, Folder 25)
- Series XVII: Rochester Daily Advertiser, Undated
  - Rochester Daily Advertiser, Undated (Box 43, Folder 26)
- Series XVIII: Sketches of Rochester, Undated
  - Sketches of Rochester, Undated (Box 43, Folder 27)
- Series XIX: Legal Documents & Notes, 1832, 1840-1851, 1857
  - Legal Documents & Notes, 1832-1857 (Bulk 1840-1851) (Box 43, Folder 28)
- Series XX: Financial Documents, 1834-1859
  - Financial Documents, Undated (Box 43, Folder 29)
  - Financial Documents, 1834-1839 (Box 43, Folder 30)
  - Financial Documents, 1840-1849 (Box 43, Folder 31)
  - Financial Documents, 1850-1859 (Box 43, Folder 32)
- Series XXI: Notes & Fragments, 1840-1859
  - Notes & Fragments, 1840-1859 (Box 43, Folder 33)
- Series XXII: Personal & Family Papers, 1832-1862
  This series contains documents concerning O'Reilly's family. It includes two scrapbooks compiled by Henry O'Reilly during the Civil War about his son, Henry Brooks O'Reilly, who was killed in the battle of Williamsburg in 1862.
  - Subseries XXII.A: Correspondence, 1838-1859
    - General, 1848, 1850, 1857 (Box 43, Folder 34)
    - Letters Received, Undated (Box 43, Folder 35)
    - Letters Received, 1838 (Box 43, Folder 36)
    - Letters Received, 1847 (Box 43, Folder 37)
    - Letters Received, 1848 (Box 43, Folder 38)
    - Letters Received, 1849 (Box 43, Folder 39)
    - Letters Received, 1850 (Box 43, Folder 40)
    - Letters Received, 1851 (Box 43, Folder 41)
    - Letters Received, 1852 (Box 43, Folder 42)
    - Letters Received, 1854 (Box 43, Folder 43)
    - Letters Received, 1857 (Box 43, Folder 44)
    - Letters Received, 1858 (Box 43, Folder 45)
    - Letters Received, 1859 (Box 43, Folder 46)
    - Letters Sent, 1848-1857 (Box 43, Folder 47)
  - Subseries XXII.B: Re Henry Brooks O'Reilly, 1851-1858
    - Correspondence, 1851-1858 (Box 43, Folder 48)
- Series XXIII: Printed Material, 1830-1859
  This series contains a variety of printed material, primarily news clippings, on miscellaneous subjects.
  - Printed Material, 1830-1859 (Box 44)
  - Printed Material, 1830-1859 (Box 45)
- Series XXIV: Items Added in 2022, 1819-1880
  Scope and Contents
  The series holds 51 volumes of documents, primarily print matter, compiled by Henry O'Reilly. As of 2022, these volumes had not been inventoried, but were added to the finding aid at that time. Generally, all the subject matter in this series is an extension of that found in other parts of the collection and in other N-YHS collections of O'Reilly/O'Rielly documents.
  36 of the volumes relate to telegraphs, including their history, legal matters, telegraph companies, and technical aspects. Several volumes of "Western Mementoes" hold print matter concerning, mostly, western New York. One of the Western Mementoes volumes concerns Iowa, specially the Demoine Navigation Company and Des Moines River.
  One volume holds documents related to the Clinton League and railroad and canal developments in New York State; three relate to agriculture; one concerns various Civil War-related matters, including the death of O'Reilly's son; one concerns the press in western New York; and one relates to political anti-Masonry.
  The container list for the series lists all the volumes. Titles in "quotations" are those used by O'Reilly. Those in [brackets] were given by the processing archivist.
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged by subject matter, beginning with volumes related to the telegraph. The telegraph portion is comprised of several "series" (e.g. "journalistic series") defined by O'Reilly. Other O'Reilly series (e.g. "agricultural series") are more directly thematic.
  Each album was given a unique identifier (e.g., SN-1, SN-2) by the processing archivists. These are intended only to facilitate reference and are not indicative of any overall numbering scheme found in the collection itself.
  - "Journalistic Series" Volume I, 1845-1847 (Offsite-box 46, Volume SN-1)
    An opening title page in this volume defines the subject of the 6 volumes in this series as "history of the establishment of the electric telegraph in the United States as furnished by the public journals during the years 1845, 46, 47, 48, 50, etc." The content consists primarily of newspaper clippings and other public print matter.
  - "Journalistic Series" Volume II, 1847 (Offsite-box 46, Volume SN-2)
  - "Journalistic Series" Volume III, 1848 (Offsite-box 46, Volume SN-3)
  - "Journalistic Series" Volume IV, 1848 (Offsite-box 46, Volume SN-4)
  - "Journalistic Series" Volume V, 1849 (Offsite-box 46, Volume SN-5)
  - "Journalistic Series" Volume VI, 1850 (Offsite-box 46, Volume SN-6)
  - "Miscellaneous Series" Volume I, circa 1847, 1858 (Offsite-box 47, Volume SN-7)
    The miscellaneous series includes a range of print matter concerning telegraphs and telegraph companies. This first volume of 7 includes some pieces circa 1847 and the entire annual report of the Smithsonian Board of Regents for 1857 (published 1858).
  - "Miscellaneous Series" Volume II, 1840s (Offsite-box 47, Volume SN-8)
    This volume holds print matter concerning the Magnetic Telegraph Company (e.g., Board of Director meeting minutes, financial statements, etc.)
  - "Miscellaneous Series" Volume III, circa 1847-1853 (Offsite-box 47, Volume SN-9)
    This volume holds print matter on various telegraph companies, among them: People's Telegraph Company, New Orleans & Ohio Telegraph Company, Lake Erie Telegraph Company, St. Louis & New Orleans Telegraph Company, Atlantic & Ohio Telegraph Company, Cleveland & Cincinnati Telegraph Company, and others.
  - "Miscellaneous Series" Volume IV, 1858-1860 (Offsite-box 47, Volume SN-10)
    This volume holds more print matter on individual telegraph companies and on telegraph history.
  - "Miscellaneous Series" Volume V, 1852-1853 (Offsite-box 47, Volume SN-11)
    This volume holds a few longer print items on the science and development of the telegraph.
  - [Miscellaneous Series. Volume VI?], 1852-1858 (Offsite-box 47, Volume SN-44)
    There is no volume marked as "Miscellaneous Series" Volume VI in this part of the collection, but the content of this volume fits within the topical framework. It includes print matter especially concerning legislation about the telegraph.
  - "Miscellaneous Series" Volume VII, 1849-1851 (Offsite-box 47, Volume SN-12)
    This volume holds longer print pieces: on the Pacific Railroad & Telegraph Company and a copy of the American Association for the Advancement of Science Proceedings of 1851.
  - "Periodical Series" Volume 1, 1852-1853 (Offsite-box 49, Volume SN-21)
    This volume holds copies of the American Telegraph Magazine, from Vol 1, No. 1 in October 1852 to Vol 1, No. 6 in June 1853.
  - "Periodical Series" Volume II, 1853-1854 (Offsite-box 49, Volume SN-22)
    This volume holds two issues of the National Telegraph Review and Operator's Companion, Vol. 1, Nos. 1 and 4.
  - "Periodical Series" Volume III, 1854-1855 (Offsite-box 49, Volume SN-23)
    This volume holds issues of Shaffner's Telegraph Companion, Vol 1, Nos. 1-4 and Vol. 2, Nos. 2-3. (Vol 2, No. 1 is not in this volume, but is noted as being in another volume with a Smithsonian report.)
  - "Legal Series" Volume I, 1848-1852 (Offsite-box 49, Volume SN-24)
    The 13 volumes of the "legal series" concern various lawsuits concerning telegraphs, perhaps especially with regard to patent claims. Unlike the following volumes, each of which seem focused on a particular case, this volume touches on various legal matters.
  - "Legal Series" Volume II, 1849 (Offsite-box 49, Volume SN-25)
    This volume relates to Alexander Bain vs. Samuel F.B. Morse.
  - "Legal Series" Volume III, 1848 (Offsite-box 49, Volume SN-26)
    This volume relates to O'Reilly et al. vs. Samuel F.B. Morse et al.
  - "Legal Series" Volume IV, 1852-1853 (Offsite-box 49, Volume SN-27)
  - "Legal Series" Volume V, 1850 (Offsite-box 49, Volume SN-28)
    This volume relates to Francis O.J. Smith vs. Hugh Downing, et al.
  - "Legal Series" Volume VI, 1851 (Offsite-box 49, Volume SN-29)
    This volume relates to Benjamin B. French, et al. vs. Henry J. Rogers, et al.
  - "Legal Series" Volume VII, 1851 (Offsite-box 49, Volume SN-30)
  - "Legal Series" Volume VIII, circa 1852 (Offsite-box 50, Volume SN-31)
    This volume relates to Samuel F.B. Morse & Alfred Vail vs. Francis O.J. Smith.
  - "Legal Series" Volume IX, 1851-1852 (Offsite-box 50, Volume SN-32)
  - "Legal Series" Volume X, circa 1852 (Offsite-box 50, Volume SN-33)
  - "Legal Series" Volume XI, circa 1852-1856 (Offsite-box 50, Volume SN-34)
  - "Legal Series" Volume XII, 1851 (Offsite-box 50, Volume SN-35)
  - "Legal Series" Volume XIII, 1851 (Offsite-box 50, Volume SN-36)
  - [Various legal matters], circa 1840s-1850s (Offsite-box 50, Volume SN-46)
    This volume was not noted as part of the "legal series" but includes print matter of contracts, leases, and other legal matters regarding telegraph companies. A notation on the inside cover indicates it was purchased for N-YHS on February 17, 1885, and so was not part of the O'Reilly donated material, but indications are that the volume was compiled by O'Reilly.
  - [Francis O.J. Smith vs. Ezra Cornell], 1871 (Offsite-box 51, Volume SN-42)
    Print matter related to this lawsuit. This copy includes O'Reilly's annotations and underlining. The underlying document is the same as the following (SN-43), but this one is missing the index.
  - [Francis O.J. Smith vs. Ezra Cornell], 1871 (Offsite-box 51, Volume SN-43)
    This document is the same as SN-42, but includes the index. This does not appear to have been O'Reilly's copy; a notation on the first page indicates that it was given to N-YHS by Francis O.J. Smith in November 1873.
  - "Dictionary Series" Volume I, 1829, 1845 (Offsite-box 51, Volume SN-41)
    The volume holds two items: "The mural diagraph, or the art of conversing through a wall" by James Swaim (1829) and "The secret corresponding vocabulary; adapted for use to Morse's electro-magnetic telegraph" by Francis O.J. Smith (1845).
  - "Dictionary Series" Volume II, 1845 (Offsite-box 51, Volume SN-47)
    The volume holds one item: "The telegraph dictionary, and seamen's signal book" by Henry J. Rogers (1845).
  - "First Series" Volume I, 1830s-1840s (Offsite-box 51, Volume SN-39)
    This volume and the next are more in the nature of scrapbooks than the other volumes here. This volume holds maps, broadsides, clippings, articles of association, stock certificates, manuscript agreements and contracts, and various print matter in connection with telegraphs. O'Reilly provides contextual notes at various points. There is an 1837 letter from Samuel F.B. Morse claiming he is the inventor of the telegraph and is seeking support for that claim.
  - "First Series" Volume II, 1840s-1850s (Offsite-box 51, Volume SN-40)
    This volume holds maps, clippings, legal agreements, pamphlets and other print matter in connection with telegraphs.
  - [Canal and railroad documents, including reports of the Clinton League], 1859-1860 (Offsite-box 51, Volume SN-48)
  - "Western Mementoes" Volume I, 1838 (Offsite-box 48, Volume SN-13)
    This volume holds one book: "Sketches of Rochester" by O'Reilly.
  - "Western Mementoes" Volume II, 1850 (Offsite-box 48, Volume SN-14)
    This volume holds one book: "Pioneer history of the Holland Purchase of Western New York" by O. Turner.
  - "Western Mementoes" Volume III, 1826, 1844, 1878 (Offsite-box 48, Volume SN-15)
    The volume holds the book "Visit to the Falls of Niagara in 1800" by John Maude (1826), with additional notes added by Maude (1844?), and inscribed by Maude to O'Reilly (1844). O'Reilly notes that the items were bound together by him in 1878.
  - "Western Mementoes" Volume IV, 1851, 1854 (Offsite-box 48, Volume SN-16)
    The volume holds two printed items inscribed by Micah Brooks to his daughter (O'Reilly's wife), Marcia: the larger item is "History of the pioneer settlement of Phelps and Gorham's Purchase, and Morris' Reserve" by O. Turner (1851); the second is an 1854 printing of "The religion of the Revolution," a 1774 discourse by David Brooks, Micah's father. There are contextual notes at the front of the volume by O'Reilly about these items and his donation to N-YHS.
  - "Western Mementoes" Volume V, 1847-1856 (Offsite-box 48, Volume SN-17)
    This volume holds various printed matter about the Des Moines River, Demoine Navigation Company, and related re: Iowa.
  - "Western Mementoes" Volume VI, 1842 (Offsite-box 48, Volume SN-18)
    This volume holds "Notices [short historical accounts] of Sullivan's campaign, or the Revolutionary warfare in Western New York" and related documents.
  - "Western Mementoes" Volume VII, 1843-1844 (Offsite-box 48, Volume SN-19)
    This volume holds three publications of the New-York Agricultural Society.
  - [New-York Agricultural Society], 1845 (Offsite-box 48, Volume SN-49)
    This volume, not marked as part of Western Mementoes or another series, holds one item: the "Transactions" of the Agricultural Society for 1844 (published 1845), which follows on the volume in Western Mementoes Volume VII.
  - "Western Mementoes" Volume VIII, 1841, 1856 (Offsite-box 48, Volume SN-20)
    This volume holds two items: "Sketches of border adventures in the life and times of Major Moses Van Campen" by John N. Hubbard (1841) and "Life of Mary Jenison: Deh-he-wa-mis" by James E. Seaver (1856).
  - "Agricultural Mementoes" Volume I, 1824 (Offsite-box 52, Volume SN-37)
    The volume holds an 1824 compilation by John S. Skinner of the newspaper American Farmer (Baltimore), issues 1819-1820.
  - "Agricultural Mementoes" Volume II, 1819-1820 (Offsite-box 52, Volume SN-38)
    The volume holds a compilation of the newspaper The Plough Boy (Albany), issues June 5, 1819 to May 27, 1820.
  - [Civil War-related print matter], 1862-1864, 1879 (Offsite-box 52, Volume SN-51)
    This volume holds:
    * Printed statements of Andrew Jackson Hamilton and Lorenzo Sherwood, legislators from Texas (1862, 1864)
    * Documents about raising "colored regiments" (1863-1864, 1879)
    * Documents about the death of O'Reilly's son, Henry Brooks O'Reilly
    * Various related clippings, notes and copies of letters.
  - "American political-antimasonry with its 'good-enough morgan'" by O'Reilly, 1880 (Offsite-box 51, Volume SN-45)
  - "Typographical Mementoes" Volume I, 1847-1876 (Offsite-box 50, Volume SN-50)
    This volume holds items related to the history of the press, printers and editors in western New York. O'Reilly provides a contextual note and index in the volume. Among the items are a manuscript memoir of publisher James D. Bemis.